Guide to the William D. Smith papers, 1816-1921 RL.11646
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William D. Smith papers
1816-1921
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, William D.
RL.11646
0.75 Linear Feet
William Doddridge Smith was a land owner, Justice of the Peace, and attorney in Clarke County, Virginia. The collection is mainly comprised of diaries, account books, ledgers, and an autograph album from several members of his extended family and covers multiple generations who lived at various times in Virginia, West Virginia, Maryland, North Carolina, and Ohio. Surnames represented are: Page, Smith, Thompson, and Williams. Three of the diaries are written by H.M. Williams (b.1842), who traveled to Cincinnati as a Christian missionary in 1882. Her diaries record her daily activities such as visiting the sick, attending meetings of various social and religious societies, and teaching Sunday school. One notebook was written by Mary Page Thompson (b. 1869) while she attended State Normal School in Baltimore (Md.) 1889, and includes notes on biology, psychology, and religion, including notes on a discussion of Christian missionary work in China. There are several items relating to Philip Doddridge Thompson (b. 1838), a Christian minister who worked in several states and one ledger that indicates that William Doddridge Smith was a Justice of the Peace in Clarke County, Virginia in 1866. The collection also includes one folder of indentures, deeds, and wills, the bulk of which was created during 1816-1854 and is related to the business and legal dealings of William Doddridge Smith and his father, Edward Jaquelin Smith, who were active in Virginia and West Virginia. There is also one folder of correspondence, photographs, clippings, and ephemera.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
William D. Smith was a land owner, Justice of the Peace, and attorny in Clarke County, Virginia. There are several other family members represented in the collection.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The William D. Smith papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1957.
Collection Overview
Mainly diaries, account books, ledgers, and an autograph album from multiple members of the Page, Smith, Thompson, and Williams families who lived in Virginia, West Virginia, Maryland, North Carolina, and Ohio. Three of the diaries are written by H.M. Williams (b.1842), who traveled to Cincinnati as a Christian missionary in 1882. Her diaries record her daily activities such as visiting the sick, attending meetings of various social and religious societies, and teaching Sunday school. One notebook was written by Mary Page Thompson (b. 1869) while she attended State Normal School in Baltimore (Md.) 1889, and includes notes on biology, psychology, and religion, including notes on a discussion of Christian missionary work in China. There are several items relating to Philip Doddridge Thompson (b. 1838), a Christian minister who worked in several states and one ledger that indicates that William Doddridge Smith was a Justice of the Peace in Clarke County, Virginia in 1866. Collection also includes one folder of indentures, deeds, and wills the bulk of which was created during 1816-1854 and is related to the business and legal dealings of William Doddridge Smith and his father, Edward Jaquelin Smith, who were active in Virginia and West Virginia. There is also one folder of correspondence, photographs, clippings, and ephemera.
Church history -- 19th century; Women -- Religious life -- United States; Women -- Diaries; Clarke County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century; West Virginia -- History -- 19th century; Kent Island (Md.) -- History -- 19th century; Oxford (N.C.) -- History; Cincinnati (Ohio) -- Religion -- 19th century; Smith, William D.; Smith, Edward J.; Williams, M. H.; Thompson, Mary Page, 1869-; Thompson, P. D., 1838-; Maryland State Normal School (Towson, Md.)
- Deeds, wills, and indentures, 1816-1854, 1910 (Box 1)
- Thompson and Smith family records, 1838-1950 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, photographs, clippings, and ephemera, 1866-1921 (Box 1)
- Records of judgments rendered by William D. Smith, Justice of Clarke County, 1866-1869, 1881 (Box 1)
- Supplies and employment ledger, 1872-1883 (Box 1)
- Account book and list of sermons preached at Markham, Emmanuel, and Leeds Chapels, 1874-1912 (Box 1)
- Account book, 1878 (Box 1)
- Mrs. C.V. Hale's estate in account with W.D. Smith committee, 1878-1880 (Box 2)
- Annie W. Smith's autograph notebook, 1881-1888 (Box 2)
- Diary of H.F. Williams, 1882-1885 (Box 2)
- Account book, 1883-1897 (Box 2)
- Supplies and employment ledger, 1884-1901 (Box 2)
- Mary P. Thompson notebook from State Normal School, 1889 (Box 2)
- Leeds Parish church ledger, 1877-1896 (Box 2)
- Diary of H.F. Williams, 1888 (Box 3)
  Scope and Contents
  Presumed to be H.F. Williams's diary by similarity of handwriting.
- Diary of H.F. Williams, 1891 (Box 3)
- Agnes P. Smith book of recipes, 1902 (Box 3)
- Attendance and gradebook, 1921 (Box 3)
- Account book, undated (Box 3)
- Guestbook, undated (Box 3)